I think I had a point of maybe maturation in my being an artist where I realized for
me it's about the activist work, specifically it has to fit with the other kind of work
I'm already would be doing.
I want to make something that I could totally make a poster of it.
I don't know if that makes sense, but I want to make things that are very in line with
what I already do.
So I ended up mostly concentrating on illustration, but then this opportunity to do this came up.
It's like this like Trans Recovery Home in West Philly called Morris Home.
They got an opportunity to have mural arts and I think other programs in the city fund
them to get two different large murals made and put up somewhere in the city.
So I got asked to do the second one.
So that's what this is.
This is like similar to the process with the performance statistics billboard.
It's pictures of folks that we're living in the house at the time and also words from
people that we're living in the house at the time.
I just took the images from this photo shoot that we did in this park one day.
This person named Angel Edwards took the pictures.
So I took the pictures and then I did a workshop where I asked them, what do you want people
to know about Morris Home?
What do you want people to know about you?
What is it really important that they get out of the mural and they gave me a lot of
words, very direct.
Then I just chose the ones I thought made sense for a mural and I put them up.
It was really intense.
Someone passed out working on it.
It was very hard.
It's probably the hardest thing project wise I've ever done.
But it is pretty awesome.
I think it's just so much of this stuff.
I started working in 2020 so I just know the internet and I'm like, oh, all the radical
ideas are like, they're like in my, they're like something during a reading I did at school,
which has meaning and value or they're like online which also has meaning and value.
But like I feel like the public space is like totally like right when you kind of, not
my kind of values, like not the values of my friends.
I don't feel like there's like a big mural of an Andre Lureford quote, maybe some
are deep in Oakland but like not every, not all over it's not common, you know.
So I thought it was like really cool to be able to like try to make something that is
like closer to like how me and like friends who are queer like, or who are leftist, like
other things like take up a lot of space and like have a lot of resources to make like
the long lasting peace about these ideas.
I will say like it's something I'm experimenting with because like the more permanent it is,
I feel like the more like you have to be.
Like I think it would be hard to have a mural of like the broken cop car with like flowers
coming out.
I do know somebody who does work like that like Jessica Sabagall in California is a mural
is two does do like some pretty rad like mural work, but I think for the most part it is,
it feels like it's easier in illustrations to like go all the way with it like what I
want to say, but I think with this, I tried to like be, yeah it was it was just cool to
be able to say like we are joyful and we feel rage and like try to make something that
was like warm and beautiful but also like honest try to be honest in that way.
And yeah, so that was like one experiment in like trying to see if I could say like something
that I really believe also on a wall, but in like a publicly funded thing where like people
have to look at this every day.
So I have to think about like what is like the best way to put that in a sentence.
I did that and I was like no I haven't done a mural sentence like not a painted one and
I feel like best part is yeah, it's just cool to get support and like funding and resources
for like some of these ideas.
That's cool.
And I think one person who was an assistant, Devon Downs was like standing with me looking
at the wall.
I think on a day when I was feeling kind of down, it was like imagine what this is going
to look like in the fall in the winter.
Like some kid is going to grow up and they're just going to have this in their neighborhood
and like that vision of like it just being a part of the landscape in a really cool way
is exciting.
Um, but yeah, I would say hardest parts were just like the physical pain.
Like there was like I have to before you install them, you have to like prime the wall,
like you prime a wall in your house or something with like these really long poles.
So because I kept bending backwards like one time my back hurts so bad I lay down and
then I couldn't like get out of bed and like it's just like a very physically intense process,
very heavy buckets of like materials getting pulled over the place like I had to get training
to work like the heavy machinery like work a lift.
It's like very very very physically hard, hot like it's 95 degrees, 90 degrees, we're
like working like it's very tough.
The process of making is very physically tough.
That's hard.
And also it's just hard like the process of making art like that, you know, like in my
life I live in a neighborhood, I live in a micro neighborhood that's very gay and my social
circles are very gay or gay adjacent.
And so I kind of bought in my life from place to place where I'm going to a space where
I'm going to be fine or like I'm transiting through places where I don't know if I will
be but like I just I don't know I don't get I'm not bothered on like transit.
But this was like different because even though that neighborhood is pretty gay like yeah
it's just different to be putting up art about trans people like in public and I think
I was very like this, you know, I'm already kind of like an introverted person and then
it was hard for me to hold the shape of the muralist like because when you're at least
advice that I got from Sammy who helped me paint it and is like way more experienced
muralist than me.
Sammy called not like she was like you know you want to be open and friendly like you're
making this new thing and like people don't know you like you have to be friendly open
to people in the neighborhood coming up and asking questions and I think because of
the topic I was very like closed but really most people were supportive pretty much up
until one of the last days when somebody with like a dog came and like was like I don't
want to see this like these people are ugly this is like a mental illness and I feel like
he like almost confirmed like the fear that I had been feeling like the whole time.
So I think that was something that was hard for me in the process but also kind of made
me think because I'm like still figuring out how I want to like be in the world as an
artist with these ideas and I think it was different to have to be accountable in public
to like what the public thinks about it.